<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saint Marie Magdalens conuersion</title>
            <author>I. C., fl. 1603.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118867</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854074</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 576:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Saint Marie Magdalens conuersion</title>
                  <author>I. C., fl. 1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English Secret Press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: I.C.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Printed with licence.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: S. Mary Magdalens conuersion.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary Magdalene, --  Saint --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19481:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19481:1"/>
            <p>SAINT MARIE MAGDALENS CONVERSION.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> IHS</p>
            <p>Printed with Licence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19481:2"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>This ſmale poeme (Gentle Reader) was compoſed for the pleaſure of ſome priuate freinds, and intended to haue bin preſented for a Newe-yeres gift the firſt of this mounth: But interuention of other affaires, delaied the finiſhing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, vntill the laſt. I made choyce of this ſubiect, as moſt fitting this time of death, the ſtile being correſpondant, plaine and paſſionate, much like a morning garment, fitting both the time and the matter. Graue enough for ſobreſt wittes, and not ſe harſhe, but may content the niceſt eares. The reading whereof (I doubt not) will proue both pleaſant, and profitable, which is as much as I can wiſh or thou deſire. <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well this laſt of Ianuarie. 1603.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thyne I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19481:2"/>
            <head>TO THE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOVT. AND VERTVOVS MISTRIS F. B. I. C. PRESENTES THIS HIS WORTHELES LABOVR <hi>for a Newe-yeares gifte.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day (the eight'h from his Natiuitie)</l>
               <l>The glorious Sonne of the Omnipotent</l>
               <l>Was Circumcis'de, bearinge mans frailetie,</l>
               <l>T'appeaſe the wrath of the Magnificent;</l>
               <l>This day, the Sonne of bleſſed MARY ſhed</l>
               <l>His firſt deare bloud, to make vs liue b'inge dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In memorie whereof this cuſtome takes,</l>
               <l>That on the firſt day of the newe-borne yeare,</l>
               <l>Eache freind, vnto his freind ſome preſent makes;</l>
               <l>Louer to Louer, huſband to his pheare:</l>
               <l>But I; poore I, that haue no gifte to bringe,</l>
               <l>Out of my home-bred Muſe theſe verſes ſinge.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19481:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19481:3"/>
            <head>SAINT MARY MAGDALENS CONVERSION.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OF Romes great conqueſt in the elder age,</l>
               <l>When ſhe the worlde made ſubiect to her thrall,</l>
               <l>Of louers giddy fancies, and the rage,</l>
               <l>Wherwith that paſſion is poſſeſt withall,</l>
               <l>When ielouſie with loue doth ſhare apart,</l>
               <l>And breedes a ciuill warre within the harte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of <hi>Helens</hi> rape, and <hi>Troyes</hi> beſeiged <hi>Towne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Troylus</hi> faith, and <hi>Creſſids</hi> falſitie,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Rychards</hi> ſtratagems for the engliſh crowne,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Tarquins</hi> luſt, and lucrece chaſtitie,</l>
               <l>Of theſe, of none of theſe my muſe nowe treates,</l>
               <l>Of greater conqueſts, warres, and loues ſhe ſpeakes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A womans conqueſt of her one affects,</l>
               <l>A womans warre with her ſelfe-appetite,</l>
               <l>A womans loue, breeding ſuch effects,</l>
               <l>As th'age before nor ſince nere brought to light,</l>
               <l>Of theſe; and ſuch as theſe, my muſe is preſt,</l>
               <l>To ſpend the idle houres of her reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou bleſſed Saint, whoſe life doth teach to liue,</l>
               <l>Intreate that louing and beſt loued Lord of thine,</l>
               <l>That he vouchſafe ſuch liuely grace to giue</l>
               <l>Vnto theſe dull, and liueles rimes of mine,</l>
               <l>That ſuch as read this good, (though ill told) ſtory,</l>
               <l>May be (like thee) for their offences ſorry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:4"/>
               <l>When firſt the worlds Creator our dread Lord,</l>
               <l>Did with his preſence bleſſe <hi>Iudeae</hi> land,</l>
               <l>And to all ſortes of people did afforde,</l>
               <l>His gratious fauour and all helping hand,</l>
               <l>Reſtoring by his power Omnipotent,</l>
               <l>The lazar, deafe, blind, lame, and impotent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Amongſt the daughters of the ſonnes of men,</l>
               <l>Shee that did moſt his gratious mercy proue,</l>
               <l>Was (<hi>Mary Marthas</hi> ſiſter) <hi>Magdalen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who loued moſt, and had moſt cauſe to loue,</l>
               <l>Her wounded ſoule he cur'de with ſinnes oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Natures deffects in others he redreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee needed not the ritch mans golden ring,</l>
               <l>That all deſires, ſeldome well gott, good,</l>
               <l>Shee needed not the Herauldes deif'ing,</l>
               <l>To make her gentle of vngentle bloud,</l>
               <l>Shee needed not the painters white and red,</l>
               <l>Nature thoſe colors in her face had ſhed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her eyes vnto their Miſtres yeelded light,</l>
               <l>All though her ſelfe, within herſelfe, were blind,</l>
               <l>Shee was nor lame, nor deafe, nor lazar-like,</l>
               <l>Perfecc'ous ſtore to each lime was aſin'de,</l>
               <l>With natures gifts ſhe plent'iouſly was graced,</l>
               <l>But ſinne thoſe ornamentes had all defaced.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sinne made her want, in middeſt of her ſtore,</l>
               <l>Sinne made her ſeruile in her libertye,</l>
               <l>Of all good graces ſinne did make her poore,</l>
               <l>And ritch in nothing but in miſery,</l>
               <l>Her ſoule was ſubiect to a thouſand euilles,</l>
               <l>Her body combred with as many Diuilles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:4"/>
               <l>But her dear Lord through his life-giuing grace,</l>
               <l>This many-headed Monſter draue away,</l>
               <l>And thoſe foule fendes who did his workes deface,</l>
               <l>His bleſſed preſence from her did affray,</l>
               <l>He thought not meete, that ſuch vnſeemely geſt,</l>
               <l>Should in ſo faire an Arbour build their neſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After her foes were thus diſperſt and gone.</l>
               <l>Her captiue ſoule b'inge franchiſ'de from their thrall,</l>
               <l>And ſhee tranſformed by that mighty one,</l>
               <l>From her life beſt' all to celeſtiall,</l>
               <l>Her Lord affirmed that her loue was ſuch,</l>
               <l>That ſhee deſerued to bee pardoned much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her Lawles luſtes ſhee chaing'de to lawfull loue,</l>
               <l>Her many pleaſures to one chiefe delighte,</l>
               <l>All other ioyes ſhee did from her remoue,</l>
               <l>And only ioyed in his bleſſed ſighte,</l>
               <l>Who beſt deſerued to bee loued moſt,</l>
               <l>Sauinge her ſoule from death, by ſinne b'inge loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee hateth nowe, what ſhee had lou'de before,</l>
               <l>Shee loueth him, to whome all loue was due,</l>
               <l>Her former miſpent life ſhee doth deplore,</l>
               <l>And nowe endeauors for to lyue anewe,</l>
               <l>Herſelfe, vnto herſelfe did hatefull growe,</l>
               <l>When thus enlight'ned ſhee her-ſelfe did knowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Holy hatred did true loue encreaſe;</l>
               <l>Shee lou'de the more in that ſhee hated ſoe,</l>
               <l>This Holy hatred did her falſe loues ceaſe,</l>
               <l>And howe to loue arighte to her did ſhowe,</l>
               <l>O Hatred thow are only good in this,</l>
               <l>In all thinges elſe thow doeſt worke amiſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:5"/>
               <l>Like to a monſter to her ſelfe ſhee ſeem'ed,</l>
               <l>And of her ſelfe, her ſelfe was now afraide,</l>
               <l>Shee ſawe 'twas otherwyſe then ſhee had deem'ed,</l>
               <l>And loth'de to ſee how fondly ſhee had ſtraied,</l>
               <l>Shee now perceaues the errors of her life,</l>
               <l>Which makes her with her ſelfe to be in ſtrife</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O how haue I deceaued beene (quoth ſhee)</l>
               <l>With the falſe ſhew of counterfeyt delight?</l>
               <l>Were theſe the pleaſures? this the vanities,</l>
               <l>Which now ſo much my gilty ſoule affright?</l>
               <l>Haue I incurr'd the loſſe of life and fame,</l>
               <l>To purchaſe ſorrow and repentant ſhame?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Did I for this, my fathers houſe forſake,</l>
               <l>Leauing my carefull ſiſter ſiſterles?</l>
               <l>Did I for this, of frendes me frendles make,</l>
               <l>Shaming my kindred through my ſinnefullnes?</l>
               <l>Did I for this, leaue ſiſter, frends and all,</l>
               <l>And from the ſeruice of my maker fall?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O ſinne, thou art a ſerpent full of fleyght,</l>
               <l>Thy face ſeem'de not ſo fowle as now I ſee,</l>
               <l>Thou doſt bewitch vs with a ſtrong deceipte,</l>
               <l>Of ſeeming good though full of miſerye,</l>
               <l>Our ſoules thou woundeſt with thy poyſonus dart,</l>
               <l>And we (as ſenceles) neuer feele the ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou art the loſſe of heauen, and hels beſt frend;</l>
               <l>How many (like a Syren) here thee ſing?</l>
               <l>How many by in chantment doſt thou ſend,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Plutoes</hi> Kingdome, ere they feele thy ſting,</l>
               <l>But why doe I exclaime againſt thee ſo,</l>
               <l>When I was partner in my ouer throw?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:5"/>
               <l>I gaue conſent that thou ſhoul'dſt worke my fall,</l>
               <l>I pleaſed was with what thou did'ſt ſuggeſt,</l>
               <l>I was attendant to ech ſeruill call,</l>
               <l>And baſely ſubiect to thy foule be-heſt,</l>
               <l>I grew a cunning Artiſt in thy trade,</l>
               <l>And with thy Charmes haue many ſoules inſnar'de.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O ſinne of ſinnes and the worſt of euills,</l>
               <l>To poyſon others with thy ſtinking breath,</l>
               <l>No meruaile though I was a lodge for Deuilles,</l>
               <l>And worthely became a hell on earth;</l>
               <l>Waſt not enoughe that thou thy ſelfe did'ſt ſinne,</l>
               <l>But that thou others to the ſame muſt winne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O my loſt ſoule, how foule wilt thou appeare,</l>
               <l>How full of feare, in that laſt dreadfull day,</l>
               <l>When thou ſhalt bitter exclamations heare,</l>
               <l>Of ſuch, whome thou did'ſt guilefully betray,</l>
               <l>What canſt thou ſay? What colour canſt thou bring,</l>
               <l>T' excuſe thy ſelfe of this infecting ſinne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O none at all; for ſinnes-ſelfe I am growne;</l>
               <l>There is no ſinne but what in me remaines,</l>
               <l>To be a publick ſinner I am knowne,</l>
               <l>The note of ſhame, which all my kinred ſtaines,</l>
               <l>The blott, which I would waſh of with my bloud,</l>
               <l>To purchaſe to my ſelfe the name of good:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But I haue bin ſo long ſinnes ſeruingman,</l>
               <l>That men will thinke I cannot from him part,</l>
               <l>They will obiect, I am a publican,</l>
               <l>And by long cuſtome grounded in the arte;</l>
               <l>From cuſtome we another nature take,</l>
               <l>In good or ill ſhee doth vs perfect make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:6"/>
               <l>If to my ſiſter home-againe I take me,</l>
               <l>Shee will reiect me, leaſt I ſpott her fame,</l>
               <l>If to my kinsfolkes, they will all forſake me;</l>
               <l>Through my miſdeedes I haue incur'de ſuch blame,</l>
               <l>I dare not to a ſtrainger ſhowe my face</l>
               <l>H' will wounde my ſoule with wordes of foule diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like to <hi>Mineruas</hi> bird, when ſhee appeares</l>
               <l>And ſhowes her hated ſelfe vnto the light,</l>
               <l>Eache fath'red foule againſt her Clamors reares,</l>
               <l>And makes her all aſhamed take her flight,</l>
               <l>They all purſuing her with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill and winge,</l>
               <l>And ſhee as faſt away doth from them flinge:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So doth it farre with me diſtreſſed one,</l>
               <l>When in the peopled ſtreets. I chaunce to walke,</l>
               <l>There man nor woman doth reſpect my moane,</l>
               <l>But all of my loſſe life doe ſeeme to talke,</l>
               <l>All ſeeme to wonder at me a I goe,</l>
               <l>And Monſter-like me to their children ſhowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Me thinkes I ſee ſome from their windowes looke,</l>
               <l>And with their fingers pointing out my ſhame,</l>
               <l>And ſome (who cannot) my foule preſence brooke,</l>
               <l>With lauiſh tounges to publiſh my defame,</l>
               <l>All handes and tounges conſpiring my diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt I a lothed Creature veyle my face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For though it bee a common act to fall,</l>
               <l>And ſinne it ſelfe is too well Cheriſhed:</l>
               <l>Yet is the ſinner hattefull vnto all;</l>
               <l>Compaſs'on now 'mong'ſt men is periſhed,</l>
               <l>The plea of mercie will not hold in lawe,</l>
               <l>Eache Pettyfogger in it findes a flawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:6"/>
               <l>The begger alwaies for offences bleedes,</l>
               <l>And feeles the hande of grim Seueritie,</l>
               <l>The ritch mans gold can cancell out miſdeedes,</l>
               <l>And blind the ſight of bleare-eyed briberie:</l>
               <l>But I am ritch in nothing, but in ſinne,</l>
               <l>That would I all forgoe ſome grace to winne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If in my life I had but once miſdone,</l>
               <l>Then had I not ſuch vrgent cauſe to mourne,</l>
               <l>Or to offend if I had newe begunne,</l>
               <l>Then were there ſome ſmale hope of backe-returne:</l>
               <l>But long vs'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſinnes from all this hope bereaues,</l>
               <l>And of their good conceptes me hopeles leaues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Much like a craſie weather-beaten boate,</l>
               <l>Who hauing all his ſayles and tacklinges loſte,</l>
               <l>Amid the ſurges of the ſeas doth floate,</l>
               <l>And too and fro with euerie guſte is toſte:</l>
               <l>So waues my anxious ſoule mid'ſt ſtormy feares</l>
               <l>No harbor can ſhee finde no calme appeares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſince of freindes my ſinnes hath me bereft,</l>
               <l>I will returne vnto that <hi>Nazarite,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who of his pitty hath good tokens left</l>
               <l>In me for lorne wretched <hi>Iſraelite,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He is for all afflicted and diſtreſt</l>
               <l>A harbor, hauen, and a port of reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A God-like man (if I may terme him ſoe)</l>
               <l>Or rather God; for dowbtles ſo he is,</l>
               <l>More then a man to bee, his deedes doe ſhowe,</l>
               <l>Eache eye his acc'ons more then humane fees:</l>
               <l>But how ſhall I bee gratefull to the beſt</l>
               <l>When I a ſinner doe my ſelfe deteſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:7"/>
               <l>For beinge good (as hee no other ſeemes)</l>
               <l>As chiefeſt good, he hateth all that's ill,</l>
               <l>Like Traytors to his crowne he ſinners deemes,</l>
               <l>Who ſtill oppoſe themſelues againſt his will;</l>
               <l>Nothing in God but ſinne can hatred breede;</l>
               <l>How then ſhall I the worſt of ſinners ſpeede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Through his all-ſeing wiſedome he doth knowe</l>
               <l>The paſſed faultes of my tranſgreſſing life;</l>
               <l>How great the woundes haue bin the Scarres will ſhowe:</l>
               <l>As yet my ſinfull ſoares are bleeding rife;</l>
               <l>More then all others, I did him offend,</l>
               <l>Leſſe cauſe there is that he ſhould ſuccor lend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What (he will ſay) now all men thee reiect,</l>
               <l>Canſt thou ſuppoſe that I will thee receaue?</l>
               <l>Mee moſt deſeruing thou did'ſt leaſt reſpect,</l>
               <l>And for a ſhadow, did'ſt the ſubſtance leaue,</l>
               <l>All that thou haſt, I gaue; yet thou vniuſte</l>
               <l>Did'ſt moſte offend him who did giue thee moſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I did Create thee of a different ſtate</l>
               <l>From other Creatures of a leſſe reſpect,</l>
               <l>I mighte haue made thee, like in forme and ſhape,</l>
               <l>Vnto the Monſters, of a feirce aſpect:</l>
               <l>But I did giue thee natures ornament</l>
               <l>Beautie, which thou haſt lauiſhlie miſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I gaue thee will, for to deſire the beſt,</l>
               <l>And vnderſtandinge to diſcerne the ſame,</l>
               <l>Thou waſt not ignorant of my beheſt:</l>
               <l>For all thy Nation inuocate my name;</l>
               <l>If thou had'ſt beene a Gentile, thy abuſe</l>
               <l>Might haue put on ſome colour of excuſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:7"/>
               <l>But thou did'ſt knowe what did to me belong,</l>
               <l>And what thy ſelfe in duty ſhould'ſt haue done,</l>
               <l>Yet thou did'ſt neuer ceaſe to worke me wrong,</l>
               <l>Perſiſtinge alwaies in thine ill begunne,</l>
               <l>I ſparinge thy deſerued puniſhment,</l>
               <l>Expectinge ſtill thy ſinnes relinquiſhment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that his Creditor hath long delay'de</l>
               <l>With dilatory hopes, of payements due,</l>
               <l>Hauing made breache of promiſe grows diſmai'de,</l>
               <l>Leaſt irefull rigor will his fault enſue,</l>
               <l>His Creditors fear'de preſence he forſakes,</l>
               <l>Tyll due repayement ſome atonement makes:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou art farre ingaged in my debt;</l>
               <l>For what haſt thou which I did not beſtowe?</l>
               <l>Hou canſt thou then newe credite now expect,</l>
               <l>Who neuer pai'ſt but euer ſeek'ſt to owe?</l>
               <l>For nowe thou com'ſt no olde debtes to defray:</l>
               <l>But mercies newe diſburſementes for to pray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Canſt thou imagine I my ſelfe forgette?</l>
               <l>Or that calme mercy reuengefull Iuſtice ſtaies?</l>
               <l>Although (tis true) I ſitt on mercies ſeate,</l>
               <l>Yet my right hand the ſword of Iuſtice ſwaies;</l>
               <l>Mercie and Iuſtice are at my diſpence,</l>
               <l>To pardon or to puniſh eache offence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou haſt already taſted mercies ſtore,</l>
               <l>In that I did ſo long thy life ſuſtaine,</l>
               <l>Now Iuſtice doth require, thou ſhould'ſt reſtore,</l>
               <l>Thy borrow'd talent, with an earned gaine,</l>
               <l>But banckrout-like, thou haſt miſpent the ſtocke,</l>
               <l>And now aſham'd at mercies gate doeſt knocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:8"/>
               <l>I knowe this Lord; I know I haue offended,</l>
               <l>And am in debted more then I can pay,</l>
               <l>I humbly craue that mercy be extended,</l>
               <l>And I no more will runne ſo fare aſtray,</l>
               <l>Teares ſpent her ſpeach (for now ſhee wept amine)</l>
               <l>And after teares ſhee thus beganne againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thou (O Lord) wilt cancell my olde debt,</l>
               <l>And once againe reſtore me to thy grace,</l>
               <l>If thou wilt all my former wronges forgett,</l>
               <l>And ſmoothe the wrinckels of thy angery face,</l>
               <l>The remnant of my purchaſ'd life I vowe,</l>
               <l>In thy true ſeruice wholy to beſtowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ſilent griefe ſuppreſt her further moane,</l>
               <l>And ſtopt the current of her flowing teares,</l>
               <l>Shee could not ſpeake, nor weepe, her ſoule alone,</l>
               <l>The heauy waight of ſorrowes burthen beares,</l>
               <l>When outward ſences once haue ſpent their ſtore,</l>
               <l>Then inward paſſions doe offlicte the more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her ſoule within her holdes a parlament,</l>
               <l>And ſummons all her powers to appeare,</l>
               <l>And they (as ready for to giue content)</l>
               <l>Vnto their Lady lend awilling eare,</l>
               <l>Within themſelues they ſeriouſly debate,</l>
               <l>How to redreſſe their miſtres troubled ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Firſt memorie (the mindes beſt Regiſter)</l>
               <l>Telles her of many (Like her ſelfe) diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>Who were reliued by this comforter,</l>
               <l>And had their former euilles all redreſt,</l>
               <l>How that the proude he vſeth to reiect,</l>
               <l>But mercies-beggars allwayes doth erect,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:8"/>
               <l>Here Hope conceaueth (from examples paſt)</l>
               <l>A good conceipt that like may now enſue,</l>
               <l>She doth ſuggeſt, how that his mercies laſt,</l>
               <l>And are beſtow'de on them that humbly ſue,</l>
               <l>Hope doth perſwade her ſad Contrition,</l>
               <l>Will for offences begge Remiſſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſtrong opinion doth poſſes her breſt,</l>
               <l>And her enſureth of a good ſucceſſe,</l>
               <l>And free-borne will (as handmaide to the reſt)</l>
               <l>Is now behinde to entertaine ſuch geſſe:</l>
               <l>Only diſtruſt and euer-douting feare,</l>
               <l>Her ſpringing hapes doe croſſe with dead diſpayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They bid her looke aright on her miſdeedes,</l>
               <l>And ſhee ſhould finde 'twas not as ſhee ſuppo'de,</l>
               <l>Which chookes in her the growth of hopefulll ſeede,</l>
               <l>And makes her doubt what earſt had beene propoſ'de;</l>
               <l>As oft as Hope her fainting ſoule imbouldes:</l>
               <l>Diſtruſt and feare the ſame as oft controwles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like to a Trau'ler in an vnknowne way</l>
               <l>Who hauing ſundrye pathes to paſſe along,</l>
               <l>Is carefull which to take, fearing to ſtray,</l>
               <l>And ſtill he doubts, that which he takes is wrong,</l>
               <l>So her ſad ſoule with doudtfull feares oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Knowes not which courſe to take but wills the beſt</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now Hope his wonted pirtie dote relate,</l>
               <l>And then Diſtruſt bids her his Iuſtice eye;</l>
               <l>Yet fearefull Hope at length doth animate,</l>
               <l>Her Conſious ſoule, his mercies doome to trye,</l>
               <l>Shee now reſolues (all feare b'eing lade aſide)</l>
               <l>Vnder his mercies winges her ſelfe to hide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:9"/>
               <l>And leaſt the vice hatefull to God and man,</l>
               <l>Ingratitude; that ill repaying ſinne,</l>
               <l>Should in her breſt erect his manſion,</l>
               <l>From forth her ſtore ſweet oyntment ſhee doth bring,</l>
               <l>Which ſhee intends vpon him to beſtow,</l>
               <l>That out-ward acte her inward loue might ſhowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee was not like thoſe ill-deſeruinge Iewes,</l>
               <l>In clenſed bodies haching leprous ſoules,</l>
               <l>Their healthes-reſtorer nine of them refuſe:</l>
               <l>But ſhee his loue within her breſt infoldes,</l>
               <l>And gratefully her precious oyle doth ſhed,</l>
               <l>On his deuine and far more precious hed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This acte of hers her Lord doth ſo regard,</l>
               <l>That he comaundes it ſhould for aye be knowne,</l>
               <l>And where his lifs true ſtorie ſhould be hearde,</l>
               <l>This deede of hers ſhould like-wiſe there be ſhowne,</l>
               <l>This acte of hers her Lorde ſomuch regarded,</l>
               <l>That he the ſame with double pay rewarded.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O what are we (o Lord) that thou ſhould'ſt way,</l>
               <l>Our dutious ſeruice at ſo high a rate,</l>
               <l>All that we borrow, Iuſtice bindes to pay,</l>
               <l>We owe thee all; from the we all did take,</l>
               <l>How comes it then that thou ſo well accep'ſts,</l>
               <l>If we diſcharge the tent'he of our due debtes?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What did ſhee giue thee; but a cruſe of oyle,</l>
               <l>Which now ſhee had no further cauſe to vſe?</l>
               <l>Shee will no more her well form'de viſage ſoile,</l>
               <l>And Natures workmanſhip by arte abuſe,</l>
               <l>But thou did'ſt weigh the loue where-with ſhee gaue it,</l>
               <l>Which made thee graciouſly vouchſafe to haue it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:9"/>
               <l>Now ſhee proceedes; and from his head deſcendes,</l>
               <l>Vnto his feete, where proſtrate ſhee doth lye;</l>
               <l>For former Pride ſhee faine would make amendes,</l>
               <l>With this deuout vnfain'de Humilitie,</l>
               <l>Shee loulie ſetts her at his bleſſed feete,</l>
               <l>Meane while her eyes riuers of teares doe weepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Teares of true ſorrowe for offences done,</l>
               <l>Her watrie eyes like prodigalles doe ſpend,</l>
               <l>Wherewith the feete of great <hi>Iehouans Sonne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For to imbalme, ſhee humblie doth intend,</l>
               <l>Thoſe feete of his, theſe teares of hers, make faire,</l>
               <l>And being wett ſhee dries them with her haire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O well ſpent teares; you did but clenſe the ſpottes,</l>
               <l>Which wery iornies, and foule waies had maide:</l>
               <l>But you did waſh of many thouſand blottes,</l>
               <l>Wherewith foule ſinne her gilty ſoule had ſmear'de,</l>
               <l>O happy teares; and happely beſtowed,</l>
               <l>You did defray what ere your miſtres owed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After this worke of Charity was paſt,</l>
               <l>Her loue was ſuch, ſhee would not from him part,</l>
               <l>No earthly ſtormes her heauenly loue could blaſt,</l>
               <l>It was ſo deeply rooted in her hart,</l>
               <l>With modeſt ſilence tempering her loues heate,</l>
               <l>Her ſilent loue by ſilence growing greate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O ſilence; Companion of the wiſe,</l>
               <l>Thou ſureſt note of ſpotles Chaſtitie,</l>
               <l>All our fraile paſſions thou doſt temporiſe,</l>
               <l>And kindleſt Holy thoughtes in ſecreſie;</l>
               <l>Thou art a vertue rarely found on earth,</l>
               <l>Of vertues ſtore there is ſo great a dearth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:10"/>
               <l>In Princes Coortes thou canſt no harbor finde,</l>
               <l>Thy ſeruice there is but of ſleighte regarde,</l>
               <l>Thou canſt not flatter; thou art not the winde,</l>
               <l>Wherewith ambitious toylinge geſtes are rear'de,</l>
               <l>Thou canſt not fill the ſailes of Enuies boate,</l>
               <l>Nor ſett the ſhip of longe-tong'de Fame a floate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou art no tradſeman for the Citties vſe;</l>
               <l>Thou canſt not harbor manie tounges in one;</l>
               <l>The Countriemen with thee haue broken truce,</l>
               <l>And entred league with fell diſſention,</l>
               <l>The woodes the babling <hi>Ecco</hi> entertaine,</l>
               <l>Which eache worde iterates and makes one twaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Both Coort and Cittie, Countrie and the woodes</l>
               <l>Are vnto Sylence ſtraingers, now vnknowne,</l>
               <l>And ſhee hath left them to their brain-ſicke moodes,</l>
               <l>And to the heauens (from whence ſhee came) is flowne,</l>
               <l>Shee ſeldome now doth viſite this our coaſte:</l>
               <l>Far if ſhee comes ſhee knowes not where to hoaſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This vertue firſt poſſeſſed <hi>Maries</hi> breſt,</l>
               <l>And did diſpoſe her vnto higher grace:</l>
               <l>For where garrulitie doth buylde her neſt,</l>
               <l>There modeſt vertues haue no biding place,</l>
               <l>By this her new-reformed life was knowne,</l>
               <l>By this hereafter conſtancie was ſhowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For when the Lord of life our Ranſome pai'de,</l>
               <l>And by his death, gaue life vnto the dead,</l>
               <l>When his Diſciples fearefully diſmai'de,</l>
               <l>From perſecutions angrie preſence fled,</l>
               <l>Shee conſtantlie attendes him to his paſsion,</l>
               <l>And feares no threates of her life-killing Nation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:10"/>
               <l>Euen at the foote of that fruit-baring tree,</l>
               <l>Which cur'de the wounde by former tree receaued,</l>
               <l>Shee humblie ſettes her downe, greiuing to ſee:</l>
               <l>His bleſſed preſence, from her thus bereaued;</l>
               <l>In ſteade of feete, ſhee powres her liberall teares</l>
               <l>On that dead truncke, which now his body beares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſhee imbraceth in her twiſted armes,</l>
               <l>Mixing her ſalt teares with his luke-warme bloude,</l>
               <l>Which from his woundes diſtil'de (to ſalue our harmes)</l>
               <l>Like forced ſtreames proceading from ſome flude,</l>
               <l>Which when ſhee ſees it makes her ſad ſoule bleede,</l>
               <l>In ſtrong compaſsion of ſo foule a deede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O thou my Lord, my Loue, my Soules delighte,</l>
               <l>Thy ſighte was earſt (quoth ſhee) my chiefeſt ioye,</l>
               <l>To ſee thee thus, it doth my ſoule affrighte,</l>
               <l>And turnes all former pleaſure to annoye,</l>
               <l>To ſee thee thus, how can I choſe but weepe</l>
               <l>When for my teares thy bloud doth waſh thy feete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How can I choſe but weepe, to ſee thy head</l>
               <l>Inuiron'de with a crowne of ſharpeſt thorne,</l>
               <l>To ſee thy louely count'nance palle and dead,</l>
               <l>Which once with beautie did the heauens adorne,</l>
               <l>To ſee the brighteſt lampes which light the skies</l>
               <l>Obſcur'de by bloud and death; thy bleſſed eyes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſee thoſe euer-working handes of thine,</l>
               <l>So ſauadglie affixed to this woode,</l>
               <l>Which with a touch, gaue lighte to blindeſt eyne,</l>
               <l>And alwaies were imploi'de in doing good;</l>
               <l>To ſee that hart, where Charitie doth dwell</l>
               <l>Peirced with Enuies ſpeare, the dart of Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:11"/>
               <l>To ſee thoſe worne but neuer-wear'ed feete,</l>
               <l>Who manie longe and toyle ſome iorneys made</l>
               <l>To ſeeke vs loſte, and euer-wandringe ſheepe,</l>
               <l>In the vaſte deſert of blacke ſinne inſnar'de,</l>
               <l>Now nether going, ſtanding, nor at reſt,</l>
               <l>But to a peece of woode with nayles addreſt;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſee that body which the pureſt wombe</l>
               <l>Of an vnſpotted Virgin, once contain'de,</l>
               <l>Now to bee fitter for ſome gaſtlie tombe,</l>
               <l>By cruell ſtripes and woundes deform'de and ſtain'de,</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe diſpiſed, naked, and for lorne,</l>
               <l>Bereft of freindes, and to thy foes a ſcorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How can I choſe (o Lord) but weepe and moane,</l>
               <l>In ſad remembrance of theſe dire aſpectes,</l>
               <l>How can I choſe but ſigh, to heare the grone,</l>
               <l>Vnder the heuie loade of our defects,</l>
               <l>Was there no other meanes to pay our loſſe,</l>
               <l>But thou muſt needes be naled to this Croſſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O wounderfull effectes, of wonderous loue,</l>
               <l>He that of late gaue life vnto the dead.</l>
               <l>And from poſſeſſed bodies did remoue,</l>
               <l>Legions of Diuelles that his preſence fled,</l>
               <l>For them that kills him, doth his life beſtow,</l>
               <l>And paies the debt, which they themſelues did owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O you vngratefull bloudy-mynded Iewes,</l>
               <l>Allwaies imbr'de in ſpilling righteous bloode;</l>
               <l>How can you thus this innocent abuſe,</l>
               <l>Who neuer in the way of ſinners ſtoode?</l>
               <l>What hath he done that you ſhould vſe him thus?</l>
               <l>Was he not euer mercifull and iuſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:11"/>
               <l>Did hee not feede the hongrie of the lande,</l>
               <l>And cure the ſicke through his health-giuinge mighte?</l>
               <l>Did hee not make the lame to goe and ſtande,</l>
               <l>And to the blinde reſtore deſired ſighte?</l>
               <l>Did not both poore, and ſicke, both lame, and blinde</l>
               <l>Through his milde pitty health and comfort finde?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O you are more in humane beaſt-like men,</l>
               <l>Then ſauadge beaſtes in wildeſt deſertes bred;</l>
               <l>They for a good deede ſtill haue gratefull ben,</l>
               <l>And ſuch as did releiue them, they haue fed:</l>
               <l>But you do pay the hire of ill deſart</l>
               <l>To him, that did all good to you impart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This maks the heauens (who earſt were bright &amp; cleare)</l>
               <l>To chainge their purple weedes to ſaddeſt blacke,</l>
               <l>No ſignes of ioye in heauen or earth appeare,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the Lord of ioye and bliſſe they lacke;</l>
               <l>The Sonne himſelfe doth hide his glorious face,</l>
               <l>Lothing to ſee his makers foule diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The earth doth tremble att this horred deede,</l>
               <l>Frighting the ghoſtes of the infernall deepe,</l>
               <l>Her wombe bringes forth ſtraing and vntimelie ſeede,</l>
               <l>The dead ariſe which in her boſome ſleepe,</l>
               <l>The adamantine rockes doe cleaue a ſunder;</l>
               <l>Their ſtonie hartes do rent to ſee this wonder:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But you whoſe hartes are harder then the rockes,</l>
               <l>You bloody actors of this tragicke ſceane;</l>
               <l>You that repay ſweete Charitie with mockes,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke his loſſe who doth your welfare meane;</l>
               <l>You neither earth belowe, nor heauen aboue,</l>
               <l>With their vnwonted prodigies can moue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:12"/>
               <l>O thou ſad mother of a ſadder Sonne,</l>
               <l>Thou art ſpectator too of this great loſſe</l>
               <l>Thy ioyes are paſt, thy ſorrowes newe-begunne,</l>
               <l>Whome once the <hi>Cribe</hi> receau'de, now beares the <hi>Croſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vnto his Birth the one did harbor tend,</l>
               <l>Vpon the other hee his Life doth ſpend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My greeued ſoule is wounded with remorce,</l>
               <l>To ſee thy ſwollen eyes; to heare thy groanes,</l>
               <l>The very ſight would flinty hartes enforce,</l>
               <l>To take compaſſion of thy bitter moanes,</l>
               <l>Thou art more like the dead, or deathes palle wife,</l>
               <l>Then to the mother of the Lord of life</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shall you and I (deare Ladie) plight our troth,</l>
               <l>And wed our ſelues to ſorrowes reſtles bed;</l>
               <l>Our loue and ioye is taken from vs both,</l>
               <l>And we are lefte for to bewale the dead,</l>
               <l>Wee both lament the loſſe of him that's gonne,</l>
               <l>I, a moſt louing Lord, thou, a bleſſed Sonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sall wee be take vs to a <hi>Heremitage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In ſome wilde deſert vnto men vnknowne,</l>
               <l>And there weare out the remnant of our age,</l>
               <l>Filling the wide woodes with our ceaſeles moane,</l>
               <l>Lette me take part of this thy heauy cheare,</l>
               <l>And for ech figh of thine ile ſpend a teare?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fellowes in miſery leſſens ſorrowes waight:</l>
               <l>But I vnworthy am to be thy mate,</l>
               <l>I haue a ſpotted ſoule with ſinnes full fraight:</l>
               <l>But thou a <hi>Virgine</hi> art <hi>Immaculate;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou art aſſin'de vnto a <hi>Virgines</hi> keeping,</l>
               <l>I will alone betake my ſelfe to weeping.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:12"/>
               <l>By that time this her ſad complaint was done,</l>
               <l>He that giues life had vanquiſh'de death by dying,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ioſeph</hi> comes t'interr this Holy one,</l>
               <l>Which in this weeper breedes newe cauſe of crying;</l>
               <l>Before ſhee wept, to ſee him ſo tormented,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhee ſees him not, ſhee now lamented:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had newe tane him from the <hi>Croſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And lai'de him in a <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of ſtone;</l>
               <l>Not his ſpent life, but his dead bodies loſſe,</l>
               <l>Is now the cauſe of this her ſecond moane,</l>
               <l>Shee ſees the tree of life of fruit bereft:</l>
               <l>But her loue-wounded ſoule vncured left.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which makes her thus to ſpeake; O ſacred tree,</l>
               <l>His precious bloud hath left thee ſanctified,</l>
               <l>Thou wert ordain'de an Aulter for to bee,</l>
               <l>Whereon this offring ſhould bee ſacrified,</l>
               <l>Since hee is gone, who was thy ornament</l>
               <l>To thee my ſad complaintes ſhall all bee bent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ile ſett thee for an obiect fore myne eyes;</l>
               <l>In ſeing thee, I ſhall not him forget,</l>
               <l>Who did vouchſafe on thee to ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>His owne deare life, to pay our ſinnefull debt:</l>
               <l>Though for my Sauiours ſhame they did thee make</l>
               <l>Yet I will honour thee for his ſweete ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With theſe and ſuch like plaintes the day was ſpent</l>
               <l>And duskie nighte had darkened all the ſckye,</l>
               <l>Which when ſhee ſawe vnto her home ſhee went,</l>
               <l>And there abſentes her from all companye,</l>
               <l>Like to a <hi>Turtle</hi> hauing loſt her mate:</l>
               <l>So ſhee without her Lord is deſolate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:13"/>
               <l>This reſtles night and <hi>Saboathes</hi> reſt b'eing paſt,</l>
               <l>(A day of ſorrowe and vnreſt to her)</l>
               <l>Vnto the Monument early ſhee did haſt,</l>
               <l>Where they his Precious Body did intier,</l>
               <l>Shee doth preſent the riſing of the ſunne,</l>
               <l>And takes her Iorney ere the day begunne,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Noe wonted daungers of the fearfull night,</l>
               <l>Coulde make her from her enterpriſe to ſtaye,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Ghoſtes</hi> and <hi>Sprites</hi> night-walkers vſe to fright,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Wolues</hi> and rauonous <hi>Beaſtes</hi> doe wach their pray,</l>
               <l>When none but murderrers and theeues did wake:</l>
               <l>Then all-alone this Pilgrimage ſhee takes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee might haue fear'de the Souldiers cruell garde,</l>
               <l>Who did about that Holy place attende,</l>
               <l>And night and day his toumbe did watch and warde,</l>
               <l>And from all <hi>Viſitores</hi> the ſame defend,</l>
               <l>But her ſtout harte theſe perilles could not touch</l>
               <l>Her loue was more, although her daunger much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loue made her ſtrong, although herſelfe were weake,</l>
               <l>Loue gaue ſwifte winges vnto her quicke deſire,</l>
               <l>Loue added fire to her former heate;</l>
               <l>Of doubtes nor daungers Loue doth not enquire,</l>
               <l>O powerfull loue, thou doſt no perilles caſt,</l>
               <l>The bitt'reſt pilles ſeeme pleaſant to thy taſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this time loue had brought her to his toumbe,</l>
               <l>Which ſhee findes open by the ſtones remoue,</l>
               <l>But nought ſhee ſees with in his emptie toumbe,</l>
               <l>But linnen cloths, which had inwrapt her loue</l>
               <l>Whome when ſhee findes not, ſhee doth weep &amp; moane,</l>
               <l>Imaginning that he was ſtolne and gone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:13"/>
               <l>O you profaine and Sacraligious theeues,</l>
               <l>Who haue (quoth ſhee) his ſacred corps bereft;</l>
               <l>It is a ſinne, to rob from him that liues,</l>
               <l>To rob the houſe of death, is dubble theft,</l>
               <l>Was not your enuy by his dying paſt,</l>
               <l>But after death the ſame muſt alſo laſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Enuy; thou art a more blaker ſinne,</l>
               <l>Then bloudy murder, who ſeekes naught but death,</l>
               <l>His thirſtie appetie hath quenſhed beene,</l>
               <l>But thou thy killing ſworde doſt neuer ſheath,</l>
               <l>The act being done he often doth relent,</l>
               <l>But thy hell-borne malice nere is ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I had not long enioy'de his bleſſed ſight,</l>
               <l>But thou did'ſt take him to the Croſſe from mee,</l>
               <l>Where hauing kill'de him in thy ſelfe diſpite,</l>
               <l>Thou ſeem'dſt content that he intomb'de ſhould bee,</l>
               <l>There did I thinke I ſhould his preſence haue,</l>
               <l>But thou haſt alſo taine him from his graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnhappie I to come no ſooner hether,</l>
               <l>I might aſwell haue come the day before,</l>
               <l>Now they haue taine him hence I know not whether,</l>
               <l>And I am neuer like to ſee him more,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spice</hi> and <hi>Oyntments</hi> which with me I brought,</l>
               <l>I cannot now beſtow on him I ſought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With this two Glorious <hi>Angelles</hi> doe appeare,</l>
               <l>To Comforte this vncomfortable one,</l>
               <l>They tell her h'is riſen, bids her not feare.</l>
               <l>But ceaſe her ſad complaintes and heauy moane,</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſhee ſtandes doubtfull of this happie newes,</l>
               <l>Her louing Lord himſelfe vnknowne ſhee vewes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:14"/>
               <l>Shee takes him to bee gard'ner of that place,</l>
               <l>And gentlie doth beſpeake him (as diſmai'de)</l>
               <l>That if he did his body thence diſplace,</l>
               <l>Hee would enforme her where the ſame was lai'de;</l>
               <l>Hee louingly diſcouers whome he is,</l>
               <l>Shee doth adore when thus her Lord ſhee ſees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her humbled body to the earth ſhee bowes,</l>
               <l>In odarac'on of his Dietie,</l>
               <l>Meane while her ioyfull ſoule her-ſelfe beſtowes</l>
               <l>In Contemplac'on of this Miſterie;</l>
               <l>Of heauenlie ioy ſhee feeles ſo ſweete a taſte;</l>
               <l>That ſhee forgettes her auncient ſorrowes paſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O thou that art the heauens and earthes Creator,</l>
               <l>Thou great diſpenſor of <hi>Caeleſtiall</hi> treaſure,</l>
               <l>Thou that of <hi>Angelles, Men,</hi> and <hi>Beaſtes</hi> art maker,</l>
               <l>Whoſe profound wiſedome hath nor end nor meaſure,</l>
               <l>How mercifull <hi>(O Lord)</hi> art thou; for each good deede,</l>
               <l>Thou doeſt repay vs with a dubble meede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee waſh'de thy feete with teares her eyes had ſhed,</l>
               <l>To clenſe her ſoule thy bloud thou did'ſt perfuſe,</l>
               <l>Shee powr'de her precious oyntement on thy hed,</l>
               <l>In her thou did'ſt <hi>Caeleſtiall</hi> grace infuſe,</l>
               <l>Shee for thy abſence did great ſorrowe take,</l>
               <l>Thou with thy preſence did'ſt her ioyfull make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Giue grace <hi>(O Lord)</hi> to me vnworthy one,</l>
               <l>To imitate this bleſſed <hi>Saint</hi> of thine,</l>
               <l>Fill thou myne eyes with teares, my hart with moane,</l>
               <l>That I may wayle thoſe greuious ſinnes of myne,</l>
               <l>And if ſalt teares vnto myne eyes be ſcant,</l>
               <l>Bee mercifull <hi>(O Lord)</hi> for this my want.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19481:14"/>
               <l>Make me (like her) all worldlie ioyes reiect,</l>
               <l>And lett my ſoule bee wedded to thy loue,</l>
               <l>Thy louing ſweetenes lett me not forgete,</l>
               <l>All other fancies from my hart remoue,</l>
               <l>And if I do not loue thee as I ſhould,</l>
               <l>Haue mercie Lord; accept of that I would.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>
               <hi>Finis Deo gratias.</hi>
               <figure>
                  <head>I. N. R. I.</head>
                  <figDesc>cross</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
